[Music]
this version the five-minute physiology
will be a little bit different cuz I'm
getting straight to the answer it's one
of the only times when I'm gonna skip
the Y in the physiology and just give
you a mole for why something is true or
not true and the reason I'm doing this
honestly it's freaking irritating if you
can tell by the emotions coming out of
me right now cuz like I thought we were
done with this conversation like 20
years ago
in fact if you have half a brain you've
seen any of the other videos and
especially if you're in class we've gone
over this concept that there are no such
things as bad exercises there's bad
application of exercises you did an
exercise with the wrong person you've
progressed too fast or too slow too much
intensity to attend volume bad technique
etc but you can't blame the exercise and
for some reason we can't get past with
this with plyometrics now if you're not
filming with that term that this means
like jumping and landing and for some
reason we think it's bad or dangerous
and we especially think it's dangerous
for kids
well it's utter nonsense I'm not really
gonna get into the detail here but I
wanted to make a video so not that you
really needed to know this but so that
you can forward this to parents or other
coaches or administrators that are
concerned about their kids doing
quote-unquote plyometrics it's just
stupid even if you look at something
like WebMD this is what I did and you
look up what are the risks of
plyometrics you can see it right there
this is the number one voted answer it's
complete and utter garbage shameful on
the person who wrote it by the way whose
name is Rehab worker Oh terrible right
you can read it for yourself but it says
things like plyometrics are very
dangerous method of exercising there are
no exceptions
that should tell you right away this
person doesn't think very well and no
exceptions really yeah and it involves
all injuries are caused by application
of excessive forces buh buh buh bah blah
the problem with pom metrics are they
cause irreversible damage really we're
the irreversible tissue damage and this
is debilitating articular cartilage is
damage that you can't come back from
what complete nutter nonsense is this so
I guess we do have to fight this battle
still the plyometrics are in fact not
dangerous if you've ever watched a kid
you realize they do this all the time
every day what do you think jump rope is
what do you think running around and
playing I mean I remember as a kid I
used to play a game just run up the tree
and jump off or run up the house in
Japan this is the whole game right
hopscotch
it's a one footed hop to a one footed
hop sometimes to put that's plyometrics
why aren't kids in tearing ACLs and have
an irreversible joint damage what do we
think we're to stop kids from running I
don't know no jumping today Sally that's
a plyometric that's dangerous stupid
right we have to think about this for
two milliseconds and realize there's
nothing going on here now any exercise I
mean you can do any exercise squatting
sit-ups push-ups planks everything is
dangerous in the wrong context water
really if you drink too much water you
can die it's called drowning so of
course if you need too many palm metrics
that can be dangerous but don't blame
the back squat because you got hurt
squatting when you squatted too much you
did it too often you got bad technique
and you did it with the wrong person
well I would say the same thing with
palm metrics or the same thing with
water don't give a four-year-old a
gallon of water and expect them not to
die of course they're gonna die but
don't blame water it's not dangerous for
you so with plow just keep a watchful
eye see my picture get it alright
watchful eye on the volume how much are
they doing so with kids we see things
like well I played AAU volleyball and
then I was on my select soccer team I
had my personal trainer I was doing my
speed clinic on the weekends and I did
all four of these in the given week and
then you wonder why my I had joint
problems with plyometrics must have been
the plows right no you just did way too
much running and jumping have nothing to
do with it
progression is the same thing right so
if you got a freshman in high schools
doing their first sport you don't need
as many you can't give them as many
ground contacts as many jumps and land
as you can as an 18 year old who's been
working with the strength coach a good
quality strength coach since they were 7
it's not total volume that always gets
used sometimes it's progression to that
volume
same thing with intensity so if you've
had a 18 year old in who was maybe
playing sports for a whole life but
she's never done any strength training
don't have her step off of a 36 inch box
land and jump
besides she can for five sets of ten our
first day you got blown to pieces right
so progression and then quality quality
is always true make sure they move well
right there's this no excuse to do any
exercise whether it's a set up or a
bicep curl with bad position of bad
technique so as long as those things are
in wrap it's pretty silly for us to say
make blanket statements like plyometrics
are dangerous and it's I would argue
irresponsible to make the comments like
the person was doing on the web MD it's
not plot metrics are dangerous you're an
idiot
I'm out